[SPEAKER_02]: These suttas are from the Samyutta Nikaya, the Connected Discourses, and this is a chapter on feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: And this sutta is called, Should Be Seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there are these three feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: What three?
[SPEAKER_02]: Pleasant feeling, painful feeling, neither painful nor pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pleasant feeling, bhikkhus, should be seen as painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Painful feeling should be seen as a dart.
[SPEAKER_02]: Neither painful nor pleasant feeling should be seen as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: When bhikkhus, a bhikkhu has seen pleasant feeling as painful, painful feeling as a dart, and neither painful nor pleasant feeling as impermanent, he is called a bhikkhu who sees rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: He has cut off cravings, severed the fetters, and by completely breaking through conceit, he has made an end to suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: One who has seen the pleasant as painful and the painful as a dart, seen as impermanent, the peaceful feeling, neither painful nor pleasant, he is a bicker who sees rightly, one who fully understands feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: Having fully understood feelings, he's taintless in this very life.
[SPEAKER_02]: Standing in the dhamma with the body's breakup, the knowledge master cannot be reckoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's what I was saying this morning.
[SPEAKER_01]: In relation to sensual pleasure, that seeing sensuality as painful, the center, the center, the core of sensual desire, that's always regarded as pleasurable, that kind of tip, that satisfaction, seeing that as painful, in a sense of
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding that pleasure to be the pain, not denying the fact that it's initially perceived as pleasurable, that will free one from sensual cravings.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, applying the same principle onto the nature of feeling in general, whereby whatever is being felt, you regard as disagreeable, because it was felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's pretty much what this sutta says.
[SPEAKER_01]: You regard pain... sorry, you regard pleasure as pain, pain as even worse thought, and neutral feeling, the peaceful feeling, you understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be controlled, it cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: It has a reason.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is... and I said that this morning, that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do that, then basically you free yourself from conceit further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards arahantship, as opposed to if you just do the same, that same principle, but in regard to the particularly central pleasure, it will free you from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you have to take this, that, that, that application onto the general level, the nature of feelings, whatever is being held, and that will free you from conceit, from the sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this sutra refers to that second, freeing yourself from conceit, the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, if you just freeze out from the seat, you'll be free from sexuality as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is... to see... to see pleasant feeling is painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is the painfulness of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's... it's afflicting you.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, when you ask like that, you're expecting to find pain in relation, or somewhere else, from that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, okay, so it's pleasant, but what is pain in there?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing left or right, up or down from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that very pleasure that is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is not seen directly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, why is it painful?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's because it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason you ask why, is because you still don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still doubting that it's painful, which means you're not seeing it as painful, thus you're asking why is it painful, how is it painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But any of the answers will not make it clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any of the answers will not make it... will not make you see it directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I can give you an answer once I see it directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can, you can, yeah, you can give an answer once you see it directly,
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to be careful whom you give that answer, because then the other person might think they understand the answer without seeing it directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you want to be accurate in describing it, it's what the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pleasure is pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that, you perceive it as pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like... like a leper regarding burning coals as pleasurable, while they were actually always painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or like...
[SPEAKER_01]: The actual perception of it was also always very disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you have to say it yourself, yeah, as investigating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As investigating it, you basically first have to see that pleasure for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, while it's simultaneously present, you have to simultaneously, while pleasure is there, you have to regard it as disagreeable, as painful, as dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another simile I was explaining to you this morning was the trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as you don't see the deadly trap hidden in it, that's meant solely for you to catch you, you will still regard aspects of that bait as agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if sometimes you might suspect that there is a trap, the fact that you are not sure, the fact that you don't see it,
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be enough for you to still regard some aspects of that bait as agreeable, as desirable, as attractive.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you suddenly... the danger becomes apparent, if you see what kind of trap it is, whereby even if you just stand and look at it, you are at the danger of being trapped, let alone if you engage with it, then you will not want anything to do with any part of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, before it was pleasant, that trap, because you didn't know it was a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it was always a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you know it's a trap and any desire towards it, it's absolutely gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know it results in a certain death.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, rather than trying to explain to you why it is a trap, you really want to
[SPEAKER_01]: Allow that phenomenon of that pleasure, of that faith, whatever it is, to arise for what it is, obviously, without engaging with the prior restraint present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if thoughts arise, you have to see them for what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to let the pleasure arise and then feel that pain, that it's revealed by the restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if... when you... when the mind stops trying to kind of run away from that pain that is revealed by the restraint, you're left
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the trap can become apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not before your mind stops trying to avoid it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people practice restraint, but when things do arise on the mental level, obviously, they're not engaging in unwholesome sensual activity with their body, but on the mental level, thoughts still might arise, and then they will be fearing them or indulging them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will not be understanding them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by neither feeling nor indulging them, by letting them arise for what they are, when you stop feeling that the risk of doing something unwholesome basically means your mind has developed in regard to those thoughts, it's not at immediate pressure by them, then you can actually see for what it is, and then you can see the agreeable as unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: The agreeables.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's... it's obviously subtle, because it involves perception, the domain of perception, the domain of feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can also regard it, basically, you can also regard it from a perception point of view, not from the feeling point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: From a perception point of view, it is being... that perception is perverted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the agreeable aspect of the central perception is actually painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: That might make more sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, being touched by that, in that manner, it's actually painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're touched.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're touched full stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're touched by the trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because giving in kills you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Giving in maintains you, keeps you in mara's domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Giving in makes you be reborn for eons and eons.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, direct result of that experience, every single misfortune that the mind can think of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that sweet tip of pleasure, or because of that seemingly agreeable, delightful perception, no matter how tiny, how small it is,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually that very tiny, tiny little perception of that delightfulness, that is the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to basically start looking at that, because everything else is management.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, explain to yourself why you shouldn't engage in such a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, obviously, you need it in the beginning, but only to bring it to the point where you can see directly that, in itself, it's actually pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arising of sensuality, of any sense, pertaining to any domain, of any kind, it's actually pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually piercing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, perception is not perverted anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, similar to the burning coil, burning coals.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that leper is basically burning himself with those coals.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he
[SPEAKER_01]: He regards that as agreeable, while it's actually always been disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's because of his disease, his assumptions, he never stops and thinks, hold on, is this really agreeable?
[SPEAKER_01]: This very center of that delightful, agreeable tip of the pleasure, he realizes, no, the fact that it presses you in that tiny, tiny manner, but a very, like, to the cold, it's actually very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It burns.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're touched by a rod, by a hot rod.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, your astral body is fine, but that bit that it touches you, it hurts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it's... obviously, if it's like a tiny bit, you might not necessarily even feel the pain initially.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just feels like a... like a... like a... like too centered, too... too concentrated.
[SPEAKER_01]: But nevertheless, it is pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you leave it a bit longer, you will see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the restraint shows.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, when you start saying no, that pain starts to build up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain of not engaging in your desire, which is actually the pain of the touch of the desire.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of the agreeable perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of the seemingly agreeable perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, people who never develop their mind, they will keep regarding restraint as the reason for the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, restraint just shows you what touches you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain touches you and that's why you can't
[SPEAKER_01]: Not give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind that's not developed can't handle pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when a desire touches you, and desire equals pain, when desire touches you, you immediately give in, because you're too painful, too painful to not give in.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is no pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pleasure is relative, eh... mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure is misperception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensual pleasure, sensual joy, sensual delight, it's all the result of perversion of perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Regarding that which is genuinely painful, regarding the touch of the painful as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no reason why.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you can free yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By seeing that actually this is unpleasant, this is painful, you will automatically stop regarding it as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, any infatuation, any desire, any lust towards it evaporates, cannot possibly remain.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're saying, too, so when experiencing an agreeable perception, do you have to re... yeah, rewriting the perception?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yeah, I was saying that this morning, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep applying the right... Rewriting, so to speak, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, restoring the right order, because now it's perverted order.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what I meant by rewriting.
[SPEAKER_02]: But seeing it is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to first allow that agreeable perception to arise for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, while that phenomenon is present, while that phenomenon is persisting, while it is changing, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: while it is enduring in your experience, which means you're mindful of it, simultaneously with that phenomenon, you regard that phenomenon in its entirety as painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: While pleasant, as painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: While agreeable, as actually disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is like finding the source of infection and right there, just right just there, applying the antibiotic, the medicine, the cream, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: As opposed to, you know, having the source of infection still covered up with dead skin or whatever else, and then you're applying... and on top of that, you're applying a medicine on a completely different body part.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not enough just to find where it is, but actually you have to uncover it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to get to that... allow that sweet, delightful, enticing center to appear, without actually pulling you in, which means the restraint, virtue, sīla, needs to be well established beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I said, you can't let your mind be engaging in distractions, even of non-sensual nature, because that remains the basis for sensuality, muddled mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the mind is not giving in to any distractions of any kind, then, all it has is what's in front of it, which is basically feelings or sensuality, for some reason or another, because those thoughts are the thoughts that will be coming up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, you haven't been running away, you haven't been obscuring them through distraction of a different kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, obviously, you haven't been compromising the restraint, the restraint of the eye faculty, nose faculty, ear and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, then, that sweet sting of desire, in regard to sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, that hits you, you kind of let it hit you, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is you then doing unwholesome things on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now we know you want, because of all the restraint and non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when it hits you, it's seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, this is pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have no choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're a victim to it hitting you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if the mind still has the assumptions of, I was hit by the pleasure, so to speak, you start seeing, yeah, that pleasure is aggressive.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pleasure is pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pleasure is attack.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pleasure is a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is not pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: A desire for pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's almost... it's kind of virtually separable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It implies the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fed through desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's virtually a dispersion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: All you need to do is sit down, having been restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having been restrained, having practiced mindfulness properly, having not been engaging in all sorts of kind of mind oblivion based meditation techniques, but actually practice clarity and composure, then when sensual thought arises, it arises in its entirety and you see through what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they bring the whole danger, the whole danger with, but still it will have that sweet center.
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's still, just that bit, it's still, okay, this is all dangerous, this is all a trap, you can say that to yourself, but the mind still regards this pleasure, this sweet center, is still the trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: This sweet, delightful tip of the pleasure is still the trap, it's still a danger, but it's still regarded as sweet, delightful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you start seeing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you do that, you recognize sweet delightful equals pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sweet delightful equals pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you don't have to do any management, because you've really uprooted that sting.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pushed out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't actually pierce you anymore, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the wound is closed, and the sting is out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like Sariputra says,
[SPEAKER_02]: What is pleasant here is that nothing is felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is pleasant in nibbāna, in that freedom, the fact that nothing is felt, is the atma's pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you see feeling as being pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by seeing so, you're completely withdrawn from it, and the mind cannot turn away towards it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's really hard for me to, like, sit down and meditate, usually.
[SPEAKER_03]: But when I'm sitting here and listening to you, like, at the same time, mind goes in and... Yeah, because that's what your meditation should be.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know, like, it's hard for me to sit down and meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: I sit down and observe my breath or do something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a completely wrong thing to do to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you have to do is understand what the dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you'll know how to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, you're trying to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: No wonder you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually good that you can't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have less of wrong notions to undo later on.
[SPEAKER_03]: But while I'm listening, do your mind get really established?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding establishes your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding is meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha always talks about... only about understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything culminates in understanding, in wisdom.
[SPEAKER_03]: And while I'm listening to you right now, I've thought of moments of pleasure sexually, moments of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, I'm repulsed by it, like I can physically feel repulsed by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's... the reason why people don't see, the reason why people maintain the perversion of perception, is because the mind is not developed in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind has never been studied, the mind has never been developed, no understanding has been initiated, nothing like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, they just carry on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even when you go to sit and meditate, you should do the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Read the sutta beforehand and then try to understand it in your... That's what meditation is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, really, remove any notion of any technique, any body watching, observing sensations, what not.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you understand, then you'll know how to continue that as practice of clarity or practice of samatha or samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still within the same right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if there's no right view, then you'll be just wasting your time, just doing some modern relaxation techniques, I guess.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it was the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, like, back in the day when people would hear the dhamma, yeah, the mind would calm down, the mind would be focused, the mind would be in samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by watching the nostrils, but by actually understanding what is being taught.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dispassion, disenchantment, cooling down, nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That results in a calm mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just how it works.
[SPEAKER_03]: I really, right now, really investigated on this sensual touch.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I almost feel like vomiting, like... Well, actually, yeah, yeah, there are dentists who do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, tele-telegraphs, they would refer to that, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you sort of, you push... well, I say pushed out, but I think, I read before, you kind of, you vomited out the sting of sensuality that was kind of deep inside of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It comes out, and it's done.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was like what Buddha gave the simile, like when you vomited food.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no desire for it anymore, once you vomited it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, when you see sensuality is painful, it's vomited food.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how much you want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Zero.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're really hungry, you will not be eating that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's horrible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is horrible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And let alone the fact that it's very dangerous.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the key, as a layman as well, indulging in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: You indulge, and then the after effect, you go, that's disgusting.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was disgusting.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, you know, there is, there is something...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the beginning, yeah, because most people don't even see it as disgusting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you've passed what you just did.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or what you did yesterday.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is... You can hear, like, when you're eating, try thinking about sexual integrals.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually disgusting while you're eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, when you're not hungry anymore, then the mind goes, goes towards, towards such fantasies.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody who is not really trained to develop their mind, just just think what you're eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you see like, oh, no, I don't want to eat this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's pretty horrible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any... any monkey, any... the monkeys, like the dogs, look at them, they don't achieve nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Horrible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But perversion of perception needs to be seen directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like what I said, pleasure needs to be seen directly, while it's present, as pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, everything else is going to be revolving around it, and it will not be approaching that center of that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just going to be managing it, while remaining stunned by it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, this sutta that I'm going to read now, needs to be connected with everything we've been talking.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's called exploration.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's how I heard on one occasion, the Blessed One was dwelling among the Kudus.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it was a town of the Kudus named Kama Sādāman.
[SPEAKER_02]: There, the Blessed One dressed the bhikkhus thus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Venerable Sir, those bhikkhus replied.
[SPEAKER_02]: Blessed One said this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you engage in inward exploration, bhikkhus?
[SPEAKER_02]: When this was said, one bhikkhu said to the Blessed One, Venerable Sir, I engage in inward exploration.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you engage in inward exploration, bhikkhu?
[SPEAKER_02]: The bhikkhu then explained, but the way he explained did not satisfy the Blessed One.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then the Venerable Ananda said, now is the time for this, Blessed One.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now is the time for this, Fortunate One.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let the Blessed One explain inward exploration.
[SPEAKER_02]: Having heard it from the Blessed One, the bhikkhus were mumbled.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, Venerable Sir, the Bhikkhus replied.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Blessed One said this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Here, Bhikkhus, when engaged in inward exploration, a Bhikkhu explores thus the many diverse kinds of suffering that arise in the world, headed by aging and death.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the source of the suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is its origin?
[SPEAKER_02]: From what is it born and produced?
[SPEAKER_02]: When what exists, does aging and death come to be?
[SPEAKER_02]: When what does not exist, does aging and death not come to be?
[SPEAKER_02]: As he explores, he understands, thus, the many diverse kinds of suffering that arise in the world, headed by aging and death.
[SPEAKER_02]: This suffering has acquisition as its source, acquisition as its origin.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is born and produced from acquisition.
[SPEAKER_02]: When there is acquisition, aging and death comes to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: When there is no acquisition, aging and death does not come to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, just to point out before, it's important to understand that acquisition means, well, loosely owning, regarding things as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Acquiring them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't mean that it's the thing's fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when people sometimes read this, they will think, oh, so I must not own anything, and they start, you know, giving away and throwing stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's... you might get rid of the stuff, but the acquisition as a phenomenon will still remain, which means then you will just appropriate something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would appropriate your status of being a beggar, or your status of not owning anything will be owned by you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not so easy
[SPEAKER_01]: As to just give up your possessions in order to be free from acquisition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Acquisition is based on mental assumption of possibility to own things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop acquiring them when you realize you can't own them in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not fully understanding that it's impossible, well, that's enough for the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't have anything practically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, it continues.
[SPEAKER_02]: He also understands aging and death, its origin, its cessation, and the way leading on, that is, in conformity with its cessation.
[SPEAKER_02]: He practices in that way and conducts himself accordingly.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is called the bhikkhu who is practicing for the utterly complete destruction of suffering, for the cessation of aging and death.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, engaging further in inward exploration, he explores thus,
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the source of this acquisition?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is its origin?
[SPEAKER_02]: From what is it born and produced?
[SPEAKER_02]: When what exists, does acquisition come to be?
[SPEAKER_02]: When what is absent, does acquisition not come to be?
[SPEAKER_02]: As he explores, he understands thus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Acquisition has craving as its source.
[SPEAKER_02]: Craving, as its origin, is born and produced from craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: When there's craving, acquisition comes to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: When there's no craving, acquisition does not come to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: He understands acquisition, its origin, its cessation, and the way leading on that is in conformity with its cessation.
[SPEAKER_02]: He practices in that way and conducts himself accordingly.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is called the beaker who is practicing for the utterly complete destruction of suffering for the cessation of acquisition.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, engaging further in inward exploration, he explores thus.
[SPEAKER_02]: When this craving arises, where does it arise?
[SPEAKER_02]: When it settles down, upon what does it settle?
[SPEAKER_02]: As he explores, he understands thus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever in the world has a pleasant and a
[SPEAKER_02]: It is here that this craving arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it arises, it is here that it settles.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it settles down.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what in the world has a pleasant and agreeable nature?
[SPEAKER_02]: The eye has a pleasant and agreeable nature in the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is here that this craving arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it arises, it is here that it settles.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it settles down.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, too, the ear, the nose, the tongue, the body and the mind have a pleasant and agreeable nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is here that this craving arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it arises, it is here that it settles.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it settles down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because whatever ascetics and Brahmins in the past regarded that in the world with the
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's just
[SPEAKER_01]: Another way, basically, of describing the Patiṭṭha Upādāna principle, just in case people are not clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: With this, this is presence of craving, presence of acquisition, presence of acquisition, manifold suffering in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Manifold suffering in the world, aging and death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief and despair.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the principle is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: When what is present, this comes to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: When craving is present, acquisition comes to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's bhikkhu bodhisattva saying, comes to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Both are actually in the present tense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, when craving is present, acquisition is.
[SPEAKER_01]: When acquisition is present, manifold suffering in the world is.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it comes to be, you kind of expect a certain amount of time to pass, but no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of craving equals presence of acquisition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of craving, absence of acquisition.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, simply by nurturing that upon which craving depends, you nurture death and everything else, at the very other end of the same principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: As it says, with regard... if they regard the world with a pleasant... as a pleasant and agreeable nature, they regard it as permanent and happiness itself, as healthy, as secure, then there's nurturing of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to go around and regard everything as horrible, despicable.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is just regard the pleasure as such, when it arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: When there is no pleasure, no need for anything, no need for any application of that medicine I was talking about before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when it's a neutral feeling, all you need to do is understand it, not engage in indolence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do not engage in distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do not run away from all of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it might sound like, oh, world is pain, world is a dart.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you regard world as pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you apply the notion of this is pain, this is pain, this is dart, only to that pleasure in regard to the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you do so, there won't be any craving in regard to the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of craving, there won't be any acquisitions in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: No acquisitions, no suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: No suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he gives a simile.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suppose, Bhikkhus, there was a bronze cup of a beverage having a fine color, aroma and taste.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it was mixed with poison.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then a man would come along, oppressed and afflicted by the heat, tired, parched and thirsty.
[SPEAKER_02]: They would tell you, good man, this beverage in the bronze cup has a fine color, aroma and taste.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it is mixed with poison.
[SPEAKER_02]: Drink it if you wish.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you drink it, it will gratify you with its color, aroma and taste.
[SPEAKER_02]: But by drinking it, you will meet with... with death or deadly suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suddenly, without reflecting, he would drink the beverage.
[SPEAKER_02]: He would not reject it, and thereby, he would meet death or deadly suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can think of the same simile.
[SPEAKER_01]: In example, imagine I come to you and I actually give you poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, I say, it tastes nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you drink it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you drink any of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I tell you, it's a deadly poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: This bottle has a poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is a poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: 100% poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has a very nice taste, apparently.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Here you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you like to drink it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Only if I was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, only if you haven't heard me, then I say it's poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, it's, you know, oh, this is a lovely drink, then you have to discern it's actually a poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: But imagine if somebody comes in, there's no lovely drink, it's straight poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: That tastes lovely, like a lovely drink.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you wouldn't even consider it as a lovely drink, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: drinkable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's a poison.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would be worth it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would be valuable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just it will not have the significance of to be drank, because it's a poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like when you see a a cup with a nice nice drink, nice juice, cocktail, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is this is a drink.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm gonna drink it, but this is a drinkable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you see a bottle with the scarlet bones on it, that's equally, probably even tastier than this drink, you still won't regard it as drinkable, because it's a poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's my point here.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you actually need to start overriding that which you regard as drinkable, as consumable, as delightful, as agreeable, as pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, not even as such, because it's a poison.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because whatever ascetics and brahmins in the past, the future or present, regarded that in their world with a pleasant and agreeable nature, as impermanent, as suffering, as non-self, as a disease, as fearful, they abandoned craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: In abandoning craving, they abandoned acquisition.
[SPEAKER_02]: In abandoning acquisition, they abandoned suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: In abandoning
[SPEAKER_02]: In abandoning suffering, they were freed from birth, aging and death.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were freed from sorrow, lamentation, pain, displeasure and despair.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were freed from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, just to reiterate, as it says there in the beginning, that which you... that which is pleasurable, they regard it as pain, as fear, as impermanent, as dangerous, as disease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not everything around you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because things that are neutral, things that are
[SPEAKER_01]: Irrelevant in terms of sensuality, in terms of pleasure, in terms of delight, in terms of attraction, you don't have to worry about.
[SPEAKER_03]: And he gives another simile.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suppose because there was a bronze cup of a beverage having a fine color, aroma and taste, but it was mixed with poison.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then a man would come along, oppressed and afflicted by the heat, tired, parched and thirsty.
[SPEAKER_02]: They would tell him,
[SPEAKER_02]: Good man, this beverage in the bronze cup has a fine color, aroma and taste, but it is mixed with poison.
[SPEAKER_02]: Drink it if you wish.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you drink it, it will gratify you with its color, aroma and taste.
[SPEAKER_02]: But by drinking it, you will meet death or deadly suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then the man would think, I can quench my thirst with water, whey, porridge or soup.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I should not drink that beverage, since to do so would lead to my harm and suffering for a long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly the point I just said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Having reflected, he would not drink that beverage, but would reject it, and thereby he would not meet death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that are not pleasurable, inciting, delightful, intoxicating, they're not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he can drink water where things that are not desirable, but serve the purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: But things that are desirable are the ones where sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically,
[SPEAKER_01]: By freeing yourself from that, by seeing the danger in desire, you free yourself from desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean you stop eating, you stop walking, you stop dressing, you stop talking, you stop doing whatever you were doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless, obviously, whatever you were doing was unwholesome, based on sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you won't be doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's exactly what that man realizes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that sweet tip of the pleasure that he has to say no, because that's where the poison is.
[SPEAKER_01]: All he has to do is drink water.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bring something else, that it's not sensuality, that it's not craved after, that it's not delighted in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something that is neutral.
[SPEAKER_03]: Saṅgha doesn't give rise to desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can only do that when you fully understand the danger of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you can spend your life eating bland food and so on, and still be bound by sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, obviously, you're not seeing that desire is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're just trying to avoid it, prevent it from arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the only way to prevent it from arising, once and for all, is to develop full dispassion in regards to it, in regard to it, not by trying to avoid things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to start by avoiding, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: by restraining, but that in itself will not lead to understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I said before, it's a necessary prerequisite, offers a basis for developing understanding, but in itself avoiding
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, still avoiding sensuality is better than engaging in sensuality, but avoiding the self will not lead to the end of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing pleasure as pain, seeing sweet as poison, that is what's going to free you from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can engage in neutral stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: Inward exploration.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I just said before he started reading that sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what meditation is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inward exploration.
[SPEAKER_01]: Figure, like, make understanding, practicing understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no method that will tell you how to do the understanding.